What's one thing that every person in this room is going to become?
ما هو الشيء المشترك الذي سيصبح عليه كل من في الغرفة حاليًّا؟
Older.
أكبر سنًّا.
And most of us are scared stiff at the prospect.
ومعظمنا يهول من الاحتمالات.
How does that word make you feel?
كيف تشعر بسماعك هذه الكلمة؟
I used to feel the same way.
كنت أشعر بنفس الطريقة.
What was I most worried about?
ما الذي كنت أكثر قلقًا بشأنه؟
Ending up drooling in some grim institutional hallway.
انتهاء الحماس داخل بعض أروقة تلك المؤسسات الكئيبة.
And then I learned that only four percent of older Americans
لكن علمت أن أربعة في المائة فقط من الأمريكيين كبار السن،
are living in nursing homes,
يعيشون في دور الرعاية،
and the percentage is dropping.
والنسبة تنخفض عما سبق.
What else was I worried about?
ما الذي يقلقني أيضًا؟
Dementia.
الخَرف.
Turns out that most of us can think just fine to the end.
اتضح أن معظمنا يستطيع التفكير بشكل جيد حتى النهاية.
Dementia rates are dropping, too.
معدلات الإصابة بالخرف تنخفض أيضًا.
The real epidemic is anxiety over memory loss.
المرض السائد حقًا هو القلق أكثر من فقدان الذاكرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I also figured that old people were depressed
أيضا اكتشفت أن كبار السن يصابون بالاكتئاب.
because they were old and they were going to die soon.
لأنهم كبار سن ولأنهم سيموتون قريبًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك).
It turns out that the longer people live,
تبين أن هؤلاء الذين يعيشون أطول،
the less they fear dying,
هم أقل خوفًا من الموت.
and that people are happiest at the beginnings and the end of their lives.
وهؤلاء الأشخاص هم الأسعد في بداية حياتهم ونهايتها.
It's called the U-curve of happiness,
يسمى المنحنى U للسعادة،
and it's been borne out by dozens of studies around the world.
وتم إثبات صحتها في العشرات من الدراسات حول العالم.
You don't have to be a Buddhist or a billionaire.
لست بحاجة لأن تكون بوذيًا أو مليونيرًا.
The curve is a function of the way aging itself affects the brain.
المنحنى هو طريقة تأثير التقدم بالعمر على الدماغ.
So I started feeling a lot better about getting older,
لذا بدأت أشعر بشكل أفضل بكثير عند التفكير بالتقدم بالسن،
and I started obsessing about why so few people know these things.
وبدأت أتوجس بسبب أن القليل من الناس يعرفون هذه الأشياء.
The reason is ageism:
السبب هو التفرقة العمرية.
discrimination and stereotyping on the basis of age.
التمييز والتنميط على أساس السن.
We experience it anytime someone assumes we're too old for something,
نحن نختبر ذلك في أي وقت يفترض شخص ما أننا مسنون جدًّا للقيام بشيء ما،
instead of finding out who we are and what we're capable of,
بدلا من البحث عن من نحن، أو عما نحن قادرين على فعله.
or too young.
أو أننا صغيرون جدًّا.
Ageism cuts both ways.
التفرقة العمرية سلاح ذو حدين.
All -isms are socially constructed ideas -- racism, sexism, homophobia --
كل التفرقات هي أفكار مبنيّة اجتماعيًّا، العنصرية، التفرقة الجنسية، رهاب المثلية...
and that means we make them up,
وهذا يعني أننا نصنع هذه التفرقات،
and they can change over time.
والتي من الممكن أن تتغير مع الوقت.
All these prejudices pit us against each other
كل هذه التمييزات تضعنا في مواجهة بعضنا البعض
to maintain the status quo,
للحفاظ على الوضع الراهن،
like auto workers in the US competing against auto workers in Mexico
مثل عاملي السيارات في أمريكا في مواجهة عاملي السيارات في المكسيك.
instead of organizing for better wages.
بدلًا من التنظيم للحصول على أجور أفضل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We know it's not OK to allocate resources by race or by sex.
نحن نعلم أنه ليس من المناسب تخصيص الموارد حسب العرق أو الجنس.
Why should it be OK to weigh the needs of the young against the old?
لماذا يجب علينا أن نثمن احتياجات الصغار أكثر من احتياجات كبار السن؟
All prejudice relies on "othering" -- seeing a group of people
كل التمييزات تعتمد على "الأخرنة"، أي رؤية مجموعة من الناس
as other than ourselves:
كآخر مختلف عنّا:
other race, other religion, other nationality.
عرق الآخر، دين الآخر، قومية الآخر
The strange thing about ageism:
الغريب في التفرقة العمرية:
that other is us.
هو أن الآخر هو نحن.
Ageism feeds on denial -- our reluctance to acknowledge
التفرقة العمرية تتغذّى على الإنكار، وعدم الرغبة بالاعتراف
that we are going to become that older person.
بأننا سنصبح ذلك الشخص الكبير بالسن.
It's denial when we try to pass for younger
إنه الإنكار عندما نحاول أن نبدو أكثر شبابًا.
or when we believe in anti-aging products,
أو عندما نصدق منتجات مقاومة الشيخوخة.
or when we feel like our bodies are betraying us,
أو عندما نشعر وكأنّ أجسادنا تخذلنا.
simply because they are changing.
ببساطة لأنها في طور التغيّر.
Why on earth do we stop celebrating the ability to adapt and grow
لماذا علينا التوقف عن الاحتفاء بقدرتنا على التكيّف والنمو
as we move through life?
بما أننا نتحرك عبر الحياة؟
Why should aging well mean struggling to look and move
لماذا يجب أن تعني الشيخوخة الكفاح من أجل مظهر وحركة
like younger versions of ourselves?
تشبه نستختنا الأكثر شبابًا؟
It's embarrassing to be called out as older
سيكون محرجًا أن ينادى عليك بالعجوز
until we quit being embarrassed about it,
حتّى نكف عن الشعور بالإحراج حوله،
and it's not healthy to go through life dreading our futures.
وليس من الصحي أن نعبر الحياة ونحن نخشى من مستقبلنا.
The sooner we get off this hamster wheel of age denial,
كذلك كلما أسرعنا في الخروج من دوّامة إنكار التقدم بالسن،
the better off we are.
كلما أصبحنا أفضل حالًا.
Stereotypes are always a mistake, of course,
وضع البشر في قوالب ثابتة خطأ بالتأكيد.
but especially when it comes to age,
خصوصًا عندما نتحدث عن العمر،
because the longer we live,
لأننا كلما عشنا أكثر،
the more different from one another we become.
أصبحنا أكثر اختلافًا عن الآخرين.
Right? Think about it.
صحيح؟ فكر بذلك.
And yet, we tend to think of everyone in a retirement home
ومع ذلك، فإننا نميل للتفكير في أن الجميع في دار للتقاعد
as the same age: old --
هم بنفس العمر: عجائز...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
when they can span four decades.
في حين أن فرق السن قد يصل لأربعة عقود.
Can you imagine thinking that way about a group of people
يمكنكم تخيل التفكير بهذه الطريقة حول مجموعة من الناس
between the ages of 20 and 60?
بين سن الـ20 و60؟
When you get to a party, do you head for people your own age?
عندما تصل إلى حفلة، هل تتوجه للناس في سنك؟
Have you ever grumbled about entitled millennials?
هل سبق لكم أن تذمرتم من عنوان جيل الألفية؟
Have you ever rejected a haircut or a relationship or an outing
هل سبق لكم أن رفضتم قصة شعر أو علاقة أو نزهة
because it's not age-appropriate?
لأنها ليست مناسبة من حيث الفئة العمرية؟
For adults, there's no such thing.
لا يوجد شيء من هذا عند البالغين.
All these behaviors are ageist.
كل هذه السلوكيات هي تفرقة عمرية.
We all do them,
ونحن جميعًا نمارسها،
and we can't challenge bias unless we're aware of it.
ولا يمكننا تحدّي التحيز إذا لم ندركه.
Nobody's born ageist,
التفرقة العمرية لا تولد معنا
but it starts at early childhood,
لكنها تبدأ في الطفولة المبكرة،
around the same time attitudes towards race and gender start to form,
بنفس الوقت الذي تبدأ فيه المواقف نحو العرق والجندر بالتشكل،
because negative messages about late life bombard us
وبسبب الرسائل السلبية حول الحياة المتأخرة التي تمطرنا بها
from the media and popular culture at every turn.
وسائل الإعلام والثقافة الشعبية على كل منعطف.
Right? Wrinkles are ugly.
صحيح؟ التجاعيد قبيحة.
Old people are pathetic.
كبار السن مثيرون للشفقة.
It's sad to be old.
من المحزن أن تكون عجوزًا.
Look at Hollywood.
انظر لهوليود.
A survey of recent Best Picture nominations
دراسة استقصائية لأحدث أفضل الصور المرشحة
found that only 12 percent of speaking or named characters
وجدت أنّه فقط ١٢ بالمائة من الشخصيات المتكلم عنهم أو المرشحين
were age 60 and up,
كانوا بعمر الستين أو أكبر،
and many of them were portrayed as impaired.
والكثير منهم تم تصويره على أنّه ضعيف.
Older people can be the most ageist of all,
الأكبر سنا قد يكونون أكثر من يفرق عمريًّا،
because we've had a lifetime to internalize these messages
لأن لدينا العمر كله لاستبطان هذه الرسائل
and we've never thought to challenge them.
ولم نفكّر أبدًا في تحديها.
I had to acknowledge it
كان علي أن أسلم بذلك
and stop colluding.
والتوقف عن التواطؤ.
"Senior moment" quips, for example:
"لحظة كبر" سخرية، على سبيل المثال:
I stopped making them when it dawned on me
توقفت عن صنعها عندما
that when I lost the car keys in high school,
فقدت مفاتيح السيارة في مدرستي الثانوية،
I didn't call it a "junior moment."
ولم أسمي تلك "لحظة شباب".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I stopped blaming my sore knee on being 64.
وتوقّفت عن لوم ركبتي المتعبة بسبب بلوغها سنّ ال64
My other knee doesn't hurt,
الركبة الأخرى لا تؤلمني،
and it's just as old.
وهي الأخرى طاعنة في السن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We are all worried about some aspect of getting older,
نحن جميعًا قلقون حول بعض مظاهر التقدّم بالسن،
whether running out of money,
سواء نفاد المال،
getting sick, ending up alone,
الإصابة بالمرض، والبقاء وحيدًا في النهاية،
and those fears are legitimate and real.
وهذه المخاوف مشروعة وحقيقيّة.
But what never dawns on most of us
ولكنّ الشيء الذي لا يدركه معضمنا
is that the experience of reaching old age
هو أن تجارب التقدّم بالسن
can be better or worse depending on the culture
يمكن أن تكون أفضل أو أسوأ اعتمادّا على الثقافة
in which it takes place.
التي تأخذ فيها مكانها.
It is not having a vagina that makes life harder for women.
ليس امتلاك المهبل هو ما يجعل حياة المرأة أصعب
It's sexism.
إنّها التفرقة الجنسية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's not loving a man that makes life harder for gay guys.
ليس حبّ رجلٍ هو ما يجعل حياة المثليين الرجال أصعب.
It's homophobia.
إنّه رهاب المثلية الجنسية.
And it is not the passage of time that makes getting older
وليس مرور الوقت هو ما يجعل التقدم في السن
so much harder than it has to be.
أصعب بكثير مما يجب أن يكون.
It is ageism.
إنّها التفرقة العمرية.
When labels are hard to read
عندما تصعب قراءة العلامات
or there's no handrail
أو عندما لا يوجد درابزين
or we can't open the damn jar,
أو لا يمكننا فتح المرطبان اللّعين،
we blame ourselves,
فنحن نلوم أنفسنا،
our failure to age successfully,
فشلنا في التقدم في السن بنجاح.
instead of the ageism that makes those natural transitions shameful
بدلًا من أنّ التمييز هو من يجعل هذه التحولات الطبيعيّة عارًا
and the discrimination that makes those barriers acceptable.
والتمييز الذي يجعل تلك الحواجز مقبولة.
You can't make money off satisfaction,
لا يمكنك كسب المال من الارتياح،
but shame and fear create markets,
لكن العار والخوف يصنعان الأسواق،
and capitalism always needs new markets.
والرأسماليّة بحاجةٍ لأسواق بشكلٍ دائم
Who says wrinkles are ugly?
من قال أنّ التجاعيد قبيحة؟
The multi-billion-dollar skin care industry.
مليارات المليارات من دولارات صناعة العناية بالبشرة.
Who says perimenopause and low T and mild cognitive impairment
من قال أنّ انقطاع الطمث وانخفاض التستوستيرون والضعف الإدراكي الخفيف
are medical conditions?
هي ظروف طبية؟
The trillion-dollar pharmaceutical industry.
تريليونات دولارات صناعة الأدوية
(Cheers)
(هتاف)
The more clearly we see these forces at work,
كلما رأينا بوضوح أكثر هذه القوى وهي تعمل
the easier it is to come up with alternative, more positive
كان من الأسهل الخروج ببديل، أكثر إيجابيّة
and more accurate narratives.
وروايات أكثر دقة.
Aging is not a problem to be fixed or a disease to be cured.
التقدم في السن ليس عيبًا ليتم إصلاحه أو مرضًا لتتم معالجته.
It is a natural, powerful, lifelong process that unites us all.
إنها سيرورة طبيعيّة قويّة تمتد بطول الحياة وتوحدنا جميعًا.
Changing the culture is a tall order, I know that, but culture is fluid.
تغيير الثقافة هي مَهمّة طويلة أعرف ذلك، لكنّ الثقافة سائلة.
Look at how much the position of women has changed in my lifetime
أنظروا كم تغيّرت مكانة المرأة خلال حياتي
or the incredible strides that the gay rights movement
أو الخطوات الرائعة لحركة حقوق المثليين
has made in just a few decades, right?
التي خطتها خلال عقودٍ قليلةٍ فقط، صحيح؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Look at gender.
انظروا إلى النوع الاجتماعي.
We used to think of it as a binary, male or female,
لقد اعتدنا أن نفكّر به كثنائيّة، ذكر أو أنثى،
and now we understand it's a spectrum.
ونحن الآن نفهم طيفه.
It is high time to ditch the old-young binary, too.
لقد حان الوقت للتخلص من ثنائية شاب وعجوز أيضًا.
There is no line in the sand between old and young,
لايوجد خط مرسوم على الرمل بين العجوز والشاب،
after which it's all downhill.
بعد كل الذي وصلت إليه الأمور.
And the longer we wait to challenge that idea,
وكلما أجلنا تحدي هذه الفكرة،
the more damage it does to ourselves and our place in the world,
كلما كان الضرر التي تتسبب به أكبر، لأنفسنا ولمكاننا في العالم،
like in the workforce, where age discrimination is rampant.
كما هو الحال بين القوى العاملة، حيث ينتشر التمييز على أساس السن.
In Silicon Valley, engineers are getting Botoxed and hair-plugged
في وادي السيليكون، يحصل المهندسون على البوتوكس وزراعة الشعر
before key interviews --
قبل مقابلة العمل الرئيسيّة
and these are skilled white men in their 30s,
وهؤلاء من الرجال البيض المهرة في الثلاثينيّات،
so imagine the effects further down the food chain.
لذا تخيلوا ما هو حجم التأثيرات أسفل السلسلة الغذائيّة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The personal and economic consequences are devastating.
إنّ العواقب الشخصيّة والاقتصاديّة مدمرة.
Not one stereotype about older workers holds up under scrutiny.
لا يوجد صورة نمطيّة واحدة عن العمال الأكبر سنًّا تصمد تحت المجهر.
Companies aren't adaptable and creative because their employees are young;
الشركات قادرة على التكيف والإبداع ليس لأنّ موظفيها من الشباب،
they're adaptable and creative despite it.
إنهم قادرون على التكيف والإبداع برغم ذلك.
Companies --
شركات...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We know that diverse companies aren't just better places to work;
نحن نعلم أن الشركات المتنوعة ليست فقط أماكن أفضل للعمل؛
they work better.
إنّها تعمل بشكل أفضل.
And just like race and sex, age is a criterion for diversity.
ومثل العرق والجنس، العمر هو مقياس للتنوع.
A growing body of fascinating research
مجموعة متزايدة من البحوث الرائعة
shows that attitudes towards aging
تشير إلى أنّ المواقف تجاه الشيخوخة
affect how our minds and bodies function at the cellular level.
تؤثر على كيفيّة عمل عقولنا وأجسادنا على المستوى الخلوي.
When we talk to older people like this (Speaks more loudly)
عندما نتحدث مع كبار السن مثل هذا (نتكلم بصوت أعلى)
or call them "sweetie" or "young lady" --
أو تسميتهم "حلوتي" أو "سيدة شابة"
it's called elderspeak --
ويسمى "كلام مع كبار السن"
they appear to instantly age,
ويظهر فورًا مع العمر،
walking and talking less competently.
المشي والحديث بكفاءة أقل.
People with more positive feelings towards aging
الناس مع مشاعر أكثر إيجابيّة تجاه الشيخوخة
walk faster,
يمشون بسرعة أكبر،
they do better on memory tests,
يكون أداؤهم أفضل في اختبارات الذاكرة،
they heal quicker, and they live longer.
يشفون بوقت أسرع، ويعيشون حياة أطول.
Even with brains full of plaques and tangles,
حتى مع أدمغةٍ مليئةٍ باللويحات والمشابك،
some people stayed sharp to the end.
بعض الناس يبقون متقدي الذهن حتّى النهاية.
What did they have in common?
ما هي القواسم المشتركة لديهم؟
A sense of purpose.
الشعور بأنّ لديهم هدف.
And what's the biggest obstacle to having a sense of purpose in late life?
وما هي أكبر عقبة تعيق الإحساس بالهدف في وقت متأخر من الحياة؟
A culture that tells us that getting older means shuffling offstage.
الثقافة التي تخبرنا بأن التقدم في السن يعني الاختفاء خلف الكواليس.
That's why the World Health Organization is developing
هذا هو السبب في أنّ منظمة الصحة العالمية تطوّر
a global anti-ageism initiative
مبادرة عالمية ضدّ التفرقة العمرية
to extend not just life span but health span.
لإطالة ليس فقط فترة الحياة ولكن أيضًا فترة العافية.
Women experience the double whammy
تختبر النساء الضربة المزدوجة
of ageism and sexism,
من التفرقة العمرية والجنسية،
so we experience aging differently.
لذلك نحن نعاني من الشيخوخة بشكل مختلف.
There's a double standard at work here -- shocker --
هناك معيار مزدوج في العمل هنا - صدمة -
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
the notion that aging enhances men and devalues women.
فكرة أن الشيخوخة تعزز الرجال وتخفض قيمة النساء.
Women reinforce this double standard when we compete to stay young,
نحن النساء نعزز هذا المعيار المزدوج عندما نتنافس على البقاء شبابّا،
another punishing and losing proposition.
عقوبة أخرى وعرض خاسر.
Does any woman in this room really believe
هل يوجد أي امرأة في هذه القاعة تعتقد حقًا
that she is a lesser version --
أنها نسخة أدنى
less interesting, less fun in bed, less valuable --
أقل إثارة للاهتمام، أقل متعة في السرير، أقل قيمة
than the woman she once was?
من المرأة التي كانت في يوم من الأيام؟
This discrimination affects our health,
هذا التمييز يؤثر على صحتنا،
our well-being and our income,
رفاهنا ودخلنا،
and the effects add up over time.
وتزداد التأثيرات بمرور الوقت.
They are further compounded by race and by class,
والتأثيرات تتضاعف أكثر حسب العرق والطبقة،
which is why, everywhere in the world,
لهذا السبب، في كل مكان في العالم،
the poorest of the poor are old women of color.
أفقر الفقراء هم نساء عجائز ملونين.
What's the takeaway from that map?
ما الذي أخذ بعيدًا من تلك الخريطة؟
By 2050, one out of five of us,
بحلول عام 2050، واحد من كل خمسة منا،
almost two billion people,
ما يقرب من ملياري شخص،
will be age 60 and up.
سيكونون بسن 60 وما فوق.
Longevity is a fundamental hallmark of human progress.
طول العمر هو السمة المميزة الأساسية للتقدم البشري.
All these older people represent a vast unprecedented and untapped market.
كل هؤلاء كبار السن يمثلون سوقًا واسعًا غير مسبوق وغير مستغل.
And yet, capitalism and urbanization have propelled age bias
ومع ذلك، الرأسمالية والمدينية تدفع بالتحيز العمري
into every corner of the globe,
في كل ركن من أركان العالم،
from Switzerland, where elders fare the best,
من سويسرا، حيث كبار السن هم الأفضل،
to Afghanistan, which sits at the bottom of the Global AgeWatch Index.
إلى أفغانستان، التي تقع في قاع مؤشر مراقبة الأعمار العالمي.
Half of the world's countries aren't mentioned on that list
نصف دول العالم لم يتم ذكرها في تلك القائمة
because we don't bother to collect data on millions of people
لأننا لا نزعج أنفسنا بجمع البيانات على الملايين من الناس
because they're no longer young.
لأنهم لم يعودوا شبابًا.
Almost two-thirds of people over 60 around the world
ما يقرب من ثلثي الناس فوق سن الـ 60 حول العالم
say they have trouble accessing healthcare.
يقولون أن لديهم مشكلة في الوصول إلى الرعاية الصحية.
Almost three-quarters say their income doesn't cover basic services
ما يقرب من ثلاثة أرباع يقولون أن دخلهم لا يغطي الخدمات الأساسية
like food, water, electricity, and decent housing.
مثل الطعام والماء والكهرباء والسكن اللائق.
Is this the world we want our children, who may well live to be a hundred,
هل هذا هو العالم الذي نريد لأطفالنا، الذين قد يعيشون لعمر المئة،
to inherit?
أن يرثوه؟
Everyone -- all ages, all genders, all nationalities --
الجميع؛ كل الأعمار، كل الجندر، جميع الجنسيات...
is old or future-old,
هم عجائز أو عجائز في المستقبل،
and unless we put an end to it, ageism will oppress us all.
وما لم نضع حدًا لها، فالتفرقة العمرية سوف تظلمنا جميعًا.
And that makes it a perfect target for collective advocacy.
وهذا يجعله هدفًا مثاليًا لدعمه بشكل جماعي.
Why add another -ism to the list when so many, racism in particular,
لماذا إضافة تفرقة آخرى إلى القائمة التي فيها الكثير، العنصرية بشكل خاص،
call out for action?
دعوة من أجل العمل؟
Here's the thing:
ها هو الأمر:
we don't have to choose.
ليس علينا الاختيار.
When we make the world a better place to grow old in,
عندما نجعل العالم مكانًا أفضل للتقدم في العمر،
we make it a better place in which to be from somewhere else,
نجعله مكانًا أفضل الذي به تكون من مكان آخر ما،
to have a disability,
لديك إعاقة،
to be queer, to be non-rich, to be non-white.
كونك شاذ، كونك لست غنيًّا، كونك لست أبيضًا.
And when we show up at all ages for whatever cause matters most to us --
وعندما نكشف في جميع الأعمار عن أي قضيّةٍ تهمنا أكثر،
save the whales, save the democracy --
إنقاذ الحيتان، حفظ الديمقراطية،
we not only make that effort more effective,
نحن لا نجعل هذا الجهد فقط أكثر فعالية،
we dismantle ageism in the process.
نحن نفكك التفرقة العمرية بهذه العملية.
Longevity is here to stay.
طول العمر هو البقاء هنا.
A movement to end ageism is underway.
إنّ حركة إنهاء التفرقة العمرية جارية.
I'm in it, and I hope you will join me.
أنا في ذلك، وآمل أن تنضموا إلي.
(Applause and cheers)
( تصفيق وهتاف)